4 days until Episode 4 deadline
I knew that she worked for Ginger!
（あるぴん）
私… お姉さんが
“ジンジャー”の人だって知ってた
I knew!
私 知ってた！
（井口(いぐち)）
う～ん なるほどね
I see...
Isn't the voice acting splendid?
（木下(きのした)）
いい声の芝居でしょ？
It makes the animation look flat by comparison.
Iguchi Yumi
Supervising Animation Director Assistant
確かに絵が負けてるかも
〝私 知ってた〞
"I knew..."
Miyamori-san, can you up the movie to the server?
宮森(みやもり)さん
ムービー
サーバーに上げといてくれる？
Yamada Masashi
Episode Director
Miyamori Aoi
Production Assistant
（あおい）
分かりました！
すぐアップロードします
Sure! I'll have it uploaded right away!
Keep building the tension...
（山田(やまだ)）
えっと たっぷりタメて…
And then let it all explode, right?
（井口）
それから感情を爆発する感じね
オーケー
Okay!
Should we focus on their anger? Or sadness?
怒りメイン？　悲しみメイン？
う～ん どっちも？
Both.
You're so brutal.
ま～たハードル高いな
いや 俺は好きですけどね 感情芝居
It should be very emotional, though.
Easier said than done.
（井口）言うのは簡単なんですよね
（山田）ああ…
Like this?
Kinoshita Shinichi
Director
（井口）
こんな？
Yeah, like that! Perfect! Great job!
そうそう それそれ！
さっすが！
I'm going to need until tomorrow morning.
アップは あした朝一くらいに
なりそうなんだけど
Wow...
Yasuhara Ema
Keyframe Animator
（絵麻(えま)）すごい…
（あおい）助かります
Thank you so much!
I was expecting early afternoon.
昼ぐらいかと思ってたよ
That's an optimistic projection,
so don't get too excited now.
私の希望的観測だから
あんまり期待しないでください
No, I'm tingling with anticipation!
いやいや 期待してるよ～
Ogasawara Rinko
Character Design
Supervising Animation Director
Ogasawara Rinko
Character Design
Supervising Animation Director
Then I shall be present at 7:00 tomorrow morning.
（小笠原(おがさわら)）
では私は朝７時に参ります
Okay!
よし！
I knew that she worked for Ginger!
（井口）私…
（絵麻）あっ
（井口）
お姉さんが
ジンジャーの人だって知ってた
I knew!
私 知ってた
No Recap Episode For Me
（いびき）
（円(まどか)）うん？
Madoka Hironori
Episode Director
Director!
監督 寝るんなら
家 帰ってくださいよ
If you want to sleep, go home!
You snore like a dying warthog!
いびき うるさいんすよ
あ～ 総集編！
ごめんなさい ごめんなさい
The recap episode!
I'm sorry! I'm sorry!
You're the one who said that
sleeping at work is inefficient!
会社での仮眠は効率悪いって
自分で言ってたじゃないっすか
And on today's to-do list...
（あおい）
やること やること　まず９話
First, for episode 9:
Check finished keyframes, package them, and in them to Yamada-san.
Exodus! #9
原画アップをチェックして
袋詰めして山田さんに回す
Exodus! #9
Exodus!
#9 Episode Director
Once he's checked them, hand them over to filming as cutting material.
山田さんの演出チェック済みを
カッティング用素材として
撮影に入れて
Filming Director
Cutting Material
Then pass those cuts to the animation director.
撮影から回収したカットは
作監に回す
Filming Director
#9 Animation Director
作監の瀬川(せがわ)さんに連絡しておく
Then I've got to call Segawa-san, the AD.
#9 Animation Director
Yoshimoto-san and Kisa-san's keyframes won't be done
until tonight's pickup, but how many cuts was that?
え～と 今日の夜便で
原画回収できないのが
吉本(よしもと)さんと木佐(きさ)さんで
何カットだっけ？
Oh right, two each!
そうだ！　それぞれ２カットずつ
That's four cuts total. I hope I can push all that to tomorrow's morning checks.
合計４カットなら あした朝からの
チェックでなんとかなるかな
Yamada-san, I'm sorry! Please make this work!
山田さん ごめんなさい
なんとかしてください
Then for episode 4...
（あおい）
それから４話
今日中に４話でやることは
Sort out the retake sheets and then check where the retake cuts are now.
#4 Retakes
R Details
リテーク表の整理
リテークカットがどこにあるか確認
#4 Retakes
R Details
Coloring
Filming
Tweening
Coloring
Filming
Tweening
Coloring
Tween
Check
Call Doumoto-san and Shinkawa-san doing tween and color check,
動画検査の堂本(どうもと)さんと
仕上げの新川(しんかわ)さんに連絡して
Coloring
Check
Tween
Coloring
Check
Tween
confirm their ETAs, and estimate when I can hand their work over to filming.
作業アップ見通し時間を確認して
撮影予定時間を読まなきゃ
Report that to Sagura-san at filming.
それを撮影の佐倉(さくら)さんに報告
Filming Director
I also gotta secure tweeners and coloring staff for the Alpine cut!
それと あるぴんカットの
動画と仕上げとスタッフの抑え
Who should I ask?
どこに頼もうかな～
I'd like it to be done nicely,
so maybe keep it in-house?
丁寧にやってもらいたいし
社内かな～
It's quite a long cut too,
so there could be a lot of frames.
尺あるから枚数
結構あるだろうな
What was it again?
えっと なんだっけ…
ハッ とにかく！
小さなことからコツコツと
Anyway, I'll never be able to finish if I never start!
Exodus! #09 Keyframe Check Chart
First, let's check the finished cuts!
まずは 上がってきた
カットのチェック！
Exodus!
Keyframe
Staff
Tween
ED
Total
Yasuhara
Animator
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Cut 79 done!
Animator
Yasuhara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Yasuhara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Yasuhara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Yasuhara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Yasuhara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Yasuhara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
カット79アップ
Animator
Yasuhara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Kohara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Kohara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Kohara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Kohara
Segawa
Effect
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Kohara
Segawa
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Animator
Kohara
Segawa
AD
SAD
Master
Raw Filming
Kohara
カット143アップ
Cut 143 done!
Kohara
Director
Ah, Kohara-san's keyframes!
Kohara
Director
あっ 小原(こはら)さんの原画だ
Kohara
Director
So cute!
かわいいな～　上手だな～
So good...
Snap out of it! No time for that just yet!
あっ ダメだ ダメだ
見とれてる場合じゃない！
Episode 9 cutting is in two days, right?
（矢野(やの)）
９話のカッティング
あさってでしょ？
Yano Erika
Production Assistant
Who's left?
残り誰が持ってんの？
Yoshimoto-san and Kisa-san.
吉本さんと木佐さんです
Yoshimoto-san will deliver,
but Kisa-san might give you trouble.
吉本さんはともかく
木佐さんはヤバいね
Huh? But when I called this morning,
he said he was on it, like he should be.
え？　でも昼間 電話した時は
元気にやってますって
Everyone knows not to trust him when he says "I'm on it" or "Just a little more."
木佐さんの“やってます”と
“あとちょっとです”は
信用するなって業界の常識
（あおい）え～！
（矢野）電話してみな
Better give him a call.
But it's so late!
（あおい）
でも こんな時間…
If he's awake, it's no big deal.
If he's not, he ought to be!
起きてたら すぐ出るし
寝てたら それこそ起こさないと
The deadline's right around the corner! Just do it!
もうギリギリなんだから
むしろ電話すべきでしょ
Roger!
はい！
ああ～ 寝てるんでしょうか
You think he's asleep?
寝てるね
He totally is.
今晩中にアップしてくれないと
ヤバいです
But he was supposed to be done with it tonight!
He's not the kind to run away though, so don't worry too much.
逃げるタイプじゃないから
そこは安心していいと思うけど
Just keep calling him.
とにかく
何べんも連絡すること
Got it!
はい　そうだ吉本さんも！
Oh right, Yoshimoto-san too!
But he lives with his parents, so I can't call this late...
…は実家だから
さすがにマズいですよね
Did you check your email?
（矢野）メールチェックした？
（あおい）メール！
My email!
miyamori@musani.jp
Inbox
Draft
Sent
Trash
RSS Feeds
Exodus
Outbox
Spam
Search
Personal Outwatch Data Files
All Unread
Today
Yesterday
Yoshimoto-san
Keyframes up
Hello, I finished episode 9's keyframes and
Okitsu Yuka
Regarding future car use
Good afternoon. In the future, the rented cars
Ochiai Tatsuya
Next oil change
Good afternoon. The car we use at production is
From
Subject
（あおい）ああっ！
（矢野）何？
What is it?
I got an email from Yoshimoto-san.
吉本さんからメール来てました
He posted the keyframes this evening.
今日の夕方
宅配便に乗せたって
はあ～
読んだはずなのに忘れてた
I read this earlier, but I totally forgot about it...
フッ ちょっと落ち着きな
You should loosen up.
Just make sure you don't overdo it
and become as airheaded as Tarou.
太郎(たろう)みたいに いっつも
のほほんとしてるのは別だけどさ
Right...
はい
I can't believe I ate so much takoyaki...
（本田(ほんだ)）
食べちゃったな～ たこ焼き
Carbs late at night are pretty bad for you, right?
夜中に炭水化物はダメだよね～
Tell that to the director.
それ監督に言ってやってくださいよ
健康診断ヤバいですよ
He's in for trouble at his next checkup.
Being busy makes him hungry.
（本田）
あの人
忙しいと食べるタイプだからな
And eating puts him to sleep.
しかも食べたら寝るタイプ
Oh right, how's episode 7 going?
Honda Yutaka
Production Manager
あっ そうだ 矢野さん
７話どうなってる？
I updated the progress chart on the server.
サーバーの進捗(しんちょく)状況表
更新しておきました
We're two days behind our pre-planned schedule, so I hope we can catch up next week.
シミュレーションと
ズレは２日なので
来週中には
巻き返せると思います
It's the first time I've asked Tanokura-san for keyframes,
but it was really top-notch work.
田之倉(たのくら)さんに
原画 初めて頼みましたけど
丁寧で すごくいいです
Hopefully that won't change.
心入れ替えたのかな～
Just don't get too complacent.
あっ でも油断は禁物だよ
Ogasawara-san's there too, so there should be no problem with the art.
小笠原さんが間に入ってますから
顔潰すようなことは
しないと思います
Let's hope you're right.
（本田）
そうだといいけどね～
As for you, Miyamori-san?
（本田）宮森さんは？
（あおい）え！
Well... I couldn't get in touch with Kisa-san a little while ago.
え～っと 今 木佐さんが
連絡つかなくて
What about episode 4? How many retakes left?
４話は？　リテーク
あと何カット残ってる？
Um... forty-five.
え～と 45カットです
う～ん
撮影には 何カット入ってる？
How many are at filming?
Seventeen cuts.
（あおい）17カットです
（本田）それ以外は？
Where are the others?
え～ 仕上げ中は８カット
Eight are at coloring check.
What about tween check?
（本田）
動画検査に入ってるカットは？
あと動画中は？
How many at the tweeners?
Tweening... tween check...
動画… 動画検査…
（本田）
撮影が終わったのは？
残りのカットは？
How many have gone through filming?
How many are left?
You don't know?
把握してないの？
Come on, please try to remember that much at least!
頼むから
それくらい頭に入れといてよ
Honda-san, stop breathing down her neck.
（本田）たあ…
（矢野）本田さん 前のめりすぎ
A total newbie can't handle that much pressure!
そんなに たたみかけたら
制作１本目の新人は
ワワッてなりますよ
You think I was pressuring her?
え？　たたみかけてた？
You so were!
かけてましたよ～
なんで そんな心配性なんですか
Why do you always worry so much?
That's just who I am.
いや～ 性分かな～
Three cuts at the tween checkers.
動画検査が３カット
動画中が２カット
Two at tweeners. Twenty left total.
残りのカットは合計20です
When can you get those to filming?
それ いつ撮影に入れられる？
For the ones at coloring and coloring check...
仕上げ検査中と
仕上げ中のカットは
半分 小諸(こもろ)スタジオに
手伝ってもらって多分 明日…
Studio Komoro are helping with half of them,
so maybe tomorrow.
I don't like maybes.
多分って困るな～
Sorry.
すみません
What did Shinkawa-san say?
新川さん なんて言ってる？
The animation's pretty tough,
so she can't give a good estimate.
内容が重いんで
上がりが読めないそうです
Is it the fireworks scene?
もしかして花火のシーン？
Yeah.
はい　それと川に流される３人を
回り込みで映したとこです
And also...
when the camera circles around the three girls in the river.
That's tough. Too tough.
重い 重いな～
Who shoved an episode like that onto a newbie, of all people?
誰だ こんな重い話数
制作１本目の新人に任せたのは～
That was you.
本田さんです
It was?!
俺か
Call Sagura-san at filming.
（矢野）撮影の佐倉さんに電話
（あおい）え？
It doesn't matter what time it is.
何時でもいいって
Just keep him updated about the situation, okay?
とにかく状況報告しておかないと
マズいっしょ
Any time's OK
Keep him updated
Call Sagura-san
Got it!
はい！
（テレビから流れる音楽）
（佐倉）はい
Okay, I got it.
了解
あしたは朝一で会社入るよ
I'll be in tomorrow morning.
Yeah, it's okay.
Sagura Yoshiki
Filming Director
うん 大丈夫
はいはい おやすみ～
Later.
Good night.
Daddy...
（大志郎(だいしろう)）
パパさん
Oh? What's wrong? Gotta pee?
お？　どうした　おしっこか？
I'm gonna pee myself!
おしっこ漏れちゃう～！
おしっこ漏れちゃう～
（ストップウオッチをとめる音）
Then go and pee!
Takanashi Tarou
Production Assistant
（太郎）
行けばいいじゃないっすか
俺じゃねえよ
あやちんだっつうの！
Not me! It's Aya-chin!
I'll never understand why some people gauge timing by yelling things out loud.
大声出して
タイミング測るヤツって俺
イマイチ分かんないんだよね
And I'll never understand how some people do it in their head.
頭ん中だけでできるヤツも
分からんけどな
I can totally do it in my head!
俺は頭ん中だけでも
大丈夫っすよ！
Shut up, Tarou.
（円･山田）
黙れよ 太郎
Good evening!
（太郎）うっ…
（あおい）お疲れさまです
Yamada-san, these are episode 9 keyframes!
山田さん ９話原画です
Check them, please!
チェックお願いします
How long do I have?
これ何時まで？
The deadline for keyframe filming is tomorrow noon.
原撮の撮影入り切りが
あしたの昼です
Tomorrow? Noon?
（山田）あした！　昼？
（あおい）え？
Wait, you already told me that.
（山田）…って前にも聞いたか
（あおい）はあ～
So heavy.
（円）ヘビーだな
（太郎）働き者っすね
Working hard, huh?
Including these, how many cuts are left for ED check in episode 9?
（山田）
９話で演出チェック残ってるのは
これ入れて何カット？
Thirty-two.
32カットです
When are the rest coming?
（山田）
残りって いつ上がる？
I can retrieve ten more by morning.
10カットは朝までに
回収できると思います
And the rest?
（山田）
残りは？
Two of the remaining four are at Kisa-san, and I can't get in touch with him.
残りの４カットのうち
２カットをお願いした木佐さんとは
ちょっと連絡 取れてないです
Kisa again?!
また木佐か！
何時まで待てばいいんだよ
How long do I need to wait?
When you're done with these cuts, you can leave for the night.
ここにあるカットを
見てもらえれば
今日は帰っていただいても
大丈夫です
The night? Technically, it's morning already.
今日はって
もう日付 変わってるけどな
What time should I come in tomorrow?
あした何時に入ればいい？
How long would it take to check the remaining fourteen cuts?
（あおい）
残りの14カット見るのに
どれくらいかかりますか？
There's Iguchi-san's retake cuts for episode 4, too.
あと井口さんの
４話リテークカットも
If I only need to check the timing of the lines, then not that long.
セリフのタイミング取るだけなら
そうかからねえよ
Episode 4 is at Iguchi-san and
Ogasawara-san, so it should be fine.
４話も井口さん 小笠原さんだし
余裕だろ
They're our best, after all.
うちのツートップっすからね
うう… ちゃんと原画上がるなら
早く入るけど
I'll come early if the keyframes will be ready.
They will! I hope...
上がります… と思います
Then I'll go home once I'm done with these.
じゃあさ このチェック終わったら
今日は いったん帰るわ
Give me a wake-up call at 6:30 tomorrow morning.
でっ ６時半に
モーニングコール頼む
I'll probably ask for one more hour,
so make sure you don't give it to me.
多分 あと１時間とか言うから
絶対 俺の言うこと
聞かないでくれ
Okay! I'll drag you out of bed if needed!
分かりました
ぶち起こします！
はあ～ あと今日中にやることは
What else do I have to do today?
Editing's the day after tomorrow,
so I should get the retakes of episode 4 done...
あさってＶ編だから
４話のリテーク終わらせて…
Retake means it's gotta be redone, right?
（ミムジー）
リテークってやり直しでしょ？
やり直しばっかり！
So much to redo.
（ロロ）
しかたないよ ミムジー
That's just how it is, Mimuji.
Sure, it would be best if they could do it perfectly on the first try,
そりゃ全部一気に
完璧なものが作れたら
それがベストだけど
なかなか そうはいかないんだよ
but it's usually never that easy.
Instead of redoing a cut over and over again,
why not settle on how to do it at the beginning?
（ミムジー）
同じカット
何べんも何べんもやり直してさ
一発でキメろよ！
Working towards completion through repeated trial and error is the only way.
（ロロ）
トライ＆エラーの繰り返しで
少しずつ完成させていくしか
ないんだよ
It seems primitive, but some things just need to be put down on paper first.
原始的に見えるけど
描かないと
分からないことだってあるんだから
A weird job for weird people.
変な仕事 変な人たち
Shoot, I passed out!
ハッ　私 今 気ぃ失ってた
Light Sweetness
Silence of the Lamps
はい
Yeah?
The Alpine cuts for episode 4 are done!
（あおい）
４話 あるぴんカット上がりました
The episode 9 keyframes are ready too!
９話の原画も届いてます
Just one more hour...
あと１時間
No.
（あおい）
ダメです
Ten minutes...
じゃあ 10分
（あおい）
絶対ダメです
Not a chance.
（山田）
お前は鬼か
Are you the devil?
I'll forge your signature and send the cuts to the next phase!
（あおい）
山田さんのサイン 勝手に書いて
勝手に流しちゃいますよ
Where'd you learn that line?!
（山田）
なんだ そのセリフ！
Who taught you that trick?!
そんな手管 誰に教わった！
Tween Checking
Correction details
Animation, Timing
Filming
ED
AD
SAD
Tween Checking
No problems. Have Miss Goth Loli check it too.
（山田）
問題なし　これゴスロリ様の
チェックもらって
Right!
はい！
Good morning, Ogasawara-san.
（あおい）
おはようございます
小笠原さん
I brought the cut for AD check.
作監チェック
よろしくお願いします
Then I shall peruse it.
拝見します
Yasuhara Ema-san.
安原(やすはら)絵麻さん
Yes?
（絵麻）はい
（あおい）え！　いたの？
You were here?
If you'd like to watch, feel free to come closer.
（小笠原）
ご覧になりたいのなら
お近くでどうぞ
え？　いいんですか？
May I?
Yes.
どうぞ
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
You just thought "That's it?" did you not?
（小笠原）
それだけと
思ってらっしゃるんでしょ？
あっ いえ…
No...
Sometimes that is all you need.
意外とそれだけで
違ってくるものなのですよ
Is tweening being done in-house?
動画は社内で？
（あおい）
はい　堂本さんにお願いしています
Yes, I asked Doumoto-san to do it.
承知しました
Understood.
Here.
Exodus!
Details: Reanimate Alpine (add more complex emotions)
Alpine
はい
Doumoto Chiemi
Tween Checker
Wake up! Wake up!
起きろ 起きろ 起きろ～
Miyamori?
（山田）宮森
（あおい）すみません！
I'm sorry!
I haven't even said anything yet.
何も言ってないだろ
Cut 51 of episode 4 needed a retake for the camerawork, right?
（山口）
４話のカット51 カメラワークの
リテーク出たはずだけど
Where is it? I didn't check it yet.
今どこにある？
まだ来てないんだけど
I'm sorry! I gave it to filming!
すいません
撮影に回しちゃってました
ハァ ハァ ハァ
I'm sorry! I'm sorry!
すいません！　すいません！
ハァ ハァ ハァ…
（あおい）うおっ
（杉江(すぎえ)）おっと
I'm sorry!
（あおい）
すいません！
Sugie Shigeru
Keyframe Animator
Careful, now.
気をつけて
Thanks a lot!
（あおい）
お疲れさまです
Wait, one package? Where's the other one?!
１つ １つ足りないです！
There should be another!
From Osaka! From Yoshimoto-san!
（あおい）
大阪から！　吉本さんから
届くはずなんです！
Yoshimoto-san?
（配達員）
吉本さん？
Road Closed
（あおい）
えっ トラブル？
Trouble?
Okitsu Yuka
General Affairs
The keyframes? Are the keyframes undamaged?
原画は？
原画は無事なんですか？
Kisa Mitsuhide
Keyframe Animator
Miyamori (Production)
What? You're only starting now?
（あおい）
え？　作業これからですか？
（木佐）
大丈夫　俺１時間で８カット
上げたことあるから
Don't worry! I did eight cuts in an hour one time!
Two cuts is nothing!
２カットくらい昼には余裕
Can I trust you?
信じていいですか？
I'll trust you and tell that to Yamada-san!
信じますから！
山田さんにも そう伝えますから！
（木佐）オーケー オーケー
（あおい）うう～ん
Okie-dokie!
はあ？　信じらんねえ
Not a chance.
I'm just not feeling it.
（木佐）
調子出ねえ～
Oh, come on, just do it! Please!
もう なんでもいいですから
お願いします！
What happened to being able to do eight cuts in an hour?
８カット上げた あのころの
木佐さんはどこに行ったんですか？
Those days, I'm afraid, are long gone.
（木佐）
あのころの俺は
お亡くなりになりました
I'm terribly sorry for being so late.
（配達員）
遅れて申し訳ございませんでした
Thanks.
しゃ～っす
Sorry I was a tad late!
（木佐）
ごめんね ちょっと遅れちゃって
Thank you very much!
（あおい）ありがとうございます
（木佐）フフフ…
1 day until Episode 4 deadline
This is Alpine's cut from episode 4, Shinkawa-san!
（あおい）
４話 あるぴんのカット
仕上げのほう
よろしくお願いします 新川さん
Editing is tomorrow?
Arakawa Nao
Color Setting / Check
（新川）
あした Ｖ編だっけ？
Yes!
（あおい）
はい！
That's soon.
フフッ ギリギリだね～
（あおい）
はい！
Yes.
You being pushed to your limit?
（新川）
もしかして せっぱ詰まってる？
Yes.
はい！
フッ 間に合わなかった作品は
ないんだから
Don't worry, every show ends up done!
Did you forget about Boing-Boing?
（太郎）
いや あったでしょ
「ぷる天」とか
Most, almost all, an overwhelming majority with only a few exceptions, get done.
ほぼ ほとんど おおむね
ごくごく一部を除いて… ない！
So don't worry!
だから冷静に落ち着いてね
（あおい）
はい
Got it!
Here it is.
ほい 来た
あ～ いいじゃん あるぴん
Look at Alpine now!
Timing correction
Mistimed lipsync
Remove nose shadow
Fix animation
Reanimate Alpine
(add more complex emotions)
Miyamori-san, how's episode 4 coming?
（本田）
宮森さん ４話どうなってる？
大丈夫です
Pretty well! Once I get the paint data from Komoro Studio,
残りは小諸スタジオに出した
仕上げデータが上がってくれば
all cuts including Alpine's will be in filming.
あるぴんカットと合わせて
撮影入り切りです
Through FTP?
ＦＴＰサーバーで？
Yes.
あっ はい
When will it be up?
何時に上がるって？
Soon.
そろそろです
We can have a rush check tonight.
夜には
ラッシュチェックできます
（電話の着信音）
（本田）小諸なら安心だね
And I know I can trust Komoro. What a relief.
Incoming call
Komoro Studio
In call
This is Musashino Animation.
はい 武蔵野(むさしの)アニメーションです
え？　ＦＴＰサーバーに
何度やっても上がらない？
You can't upload it to the FTP server?
今日中には無理？
You can't do it today?!
あっ はい 分かりました
よろしくお願いします
Right. I understand.
Thank you.
Most... Almost all... An overwhelming majority...
ほぼ… ほとんど… おおむね
Tea stains are so annoying.
（あおい）
茶渋 気になるよね～
Yeah, I agree.
なるなる　茶渋なんて
この世から消え去ればいいのに
Tea stains should disappear from this universe.
Yeah, I agree.
ホント ホント
The universe should disappear too.
ついでに世界も
消え去ればいいのにね
Yeah, I agree.
ホント ホント… え？
If everything just disappeared, it'd be such a relief.
（あおい）
全部 消え去れば
スッキリするのに…
Meowmori, what are you doing?
みゃーもり？
あんた何やってるの？
うんっ 宮森！
ちょっと こっち来な
Come here for a sec, Miyamori.
（あおい）
はい
Okay.
Oosasa Jelly
Eat this.
（矢野）
これ食べな
Oosasa Jelly
Uh, jelly?
え～と ようかん？
Your brain's not working right, is it?
（矢野）
あんた もう脳みそ
動いてないっしょ　糖分取りな
Get some sugar in the blood.
Right.
はい
（矢野）皮むいて
（あおい）ああ…
Take off the wrapper first!
So?
What's wrong? What's going on?
（矢野）
どうしたの？　どうなってんの？
Um...
（あおい）
えっと…
（あおい）うう～
（矢野）しっかり！　４話は？
Get a grip! How's episode 4?
Ah... Um...
あの えっと…
ハッ 万策尽きました
I'm out of ideas!
That's the PM's line! Not yours!
それはデスクのセリフ
尽きてない！
ハッ でも放送できないかも
But it might not make it on air!
What's the reason? I'm asking you why you're saying that!
だから なんで！
何をもって
放送できないと言うのか！
I don't know.
分かりません
Just tell me what's happening.
（矢野）
状況を報告せよ
You know episode 4 and 9 the best.
４話と９話を一番よく知ってるのは
みゃーもりなんだから
Calm down and think about it.
落ち着いて思い出せ
Episode 4 is done for if you break down!
みゃーもりが動いてこそ
４話は完パケるんだよ！
There has been an FTP error.
Cannot connect to host.
Huh?
あれ？
Ochiai Tatsuya
Production Assistant
Honda-san, did you change the server password?
本田さん サーバーの
パスワードとかいじりました？
No, why?
いや なんで？
I can't connect.
（太郎）
サーバーに
つながらないんすよ
（落合(おちあい)）
今朝からな
Been like that all morning.
Seriously?
（太郎）
マジっすか？
Did you tell the admins?
システムには連絡したの？
They can't get in touch with the hosting company.
ずっとレンタルサーバー会社と
連絡がつかないらしいですよ
They're looking for info online.
ネットの情報
追っかけてますけど
What's wrong with the server? A blackout?
サーバーどうなってんだよ
停電か？
The lights are all on.
（円）電気ついてんじゃないっすか
（木下）おっ
What about the FTP?
（本田）
ＦＴＰは？
It's down.
（落合）
ダメですね
I can't get the paint data from Komoro.
小諸スタジオの
仕上げデータが引っ張れない
They're out in the sticks.
地方だからな～
If the server's down, how about using Giga Data Mail?
サーバーがダメなら
ギガデータ便 使って
They're trying, but the speed there isn't all that great.
やってますけど そっちも
スピードが出ないらしいです
When will you be able to download it?
じゃあ いつ
ダウンロードできるの？
あと20時間くらいですかね
In twenty hours or so.
Wow, really?
（太郎）マジっすか！
（本田）なんで？
Why?!
I don't know.
さあ 小諸のシステム担当は
The admin at Komoro says it must be a
configuration error at the Hikari Fiber router.
光ファイバーの分配器の
トラブルじゃないかと
He's already contacted TNN and the ISP about it.
ＴＮＮとプロバイダーに
原因を調べてもらってるらしいです
（太郎）
ありゃりゃ…
トラブルって重なるもんっすね
Trouble never walks alone.
They got in touch with the rental server's admin.
レンタルサーバーの担当者と
連絡がついたようです
When is it coming back?
いつ復旧するって？
They don't have a clue. The server's totally shot.
見通し立たずです
サーバーが飛んだらしいです
あ～あ…
Shortkey search
The backup! What about the backup?
（本田）
バックアップ！　バックアップは？
025  Komoro Studio
026  R&B
027  Kisa-san
028  Badjob
Komoro Studio
Calling
（矢野）それも一緒に
（太郎）ええ～
That's gone too.
And the mirror?
ミラーサーバーの
データがあるだろう？
That too.
それもボン
Are you kidding me?! This can't be real!
ありえないよ　なんだよ それ！
これだからデータは怖いね
This is why I don't trust data.
Episode 6 should be fine, Ochiai. Episode 4's in trouble, though.
落合の６話よりも今
一番ピンチなのはみゃーもり
You asked Komoro too, didn't you, Meowmori?
あんたも小諸に出してたでしょ？
They can't upload episode 4's retake paint data to the server.
４話のリテークカットの
仕上げデータが
サーバーにあげられません
So I can't hand it over to filming today.
なので今日の撮入れは無理です
It won't make it to editing tomorrow.
あしたのＶ編 納品に…
間に合いません
I'm out of ideas!
万策尽きた～！
And the first two episodes were so popular...
２話まで評判いいのに
We finally had a chance to show that Musani isn't just riding its former glory and reputation!
過去の栄光にすがりつくしか
ないとか言われてるムサニが
せっかく底力を見せる
チャンスだったのに～！
Man, something here must be jinxing us with all sorts of bad luck!
すげ～ 絶対この中に
最強最悪の疫病神がいるんすよ
（落合･本田）お前だろ！
（矢野）あんただろ！
It's you!
Seriously?
マジっすか
（興津(おきつ)）
４話のリテークデータ
Komoro still had the episode 4 retake data on their local hard drives.
小諸のローカルの
ハードディスクには
残ってるそうです
Their president will bring the hard drive here by car now.
社長さんが今からハードディスクを
車で運んでくださるそうです
How long's the trip?
到着は？
At least two and a half hours if they take the highway.
小諸からだと高速使って
２時間半でしょうか
あっ ９話の
カッティング行かなきゃ
I need to go to today's cutting!
Stop!
（矢野）
ストップ
You know the most about episode 4!
You can't up and leave like that!
４話の状況を一番つかんでるのは
あんたなんだから
会社にいなくて どうすんの？
But...
（あおい）でも…
（矢野）いいから！
Sit down, will you?
You can't do this all by yourself!
アニメは一人で
作ってるんじゃないんだよ！
Anime production is a team effort!
アニメ制作は
チームワークなんだ！
Team...
チーム…
Just call Sagura-san and tell him the material will be late.
とりあえず佐倉さんに
撮入れ遅れますって連絡して
Right.
あっ はい！
（本田）
９話の作監入れと回収
Then for episode 9's animation director check.
This is Miyamori from production.
Tarou, go pick up the cuts from Segawa-san.
瀬川さんとこは太郎
きみ 行って
I'm sorry, but we're having FTP connection issues and can't get the paint data.
あ？　対 瀬川用に
とうとう秘密兵器を出しますか
So you're deploying the ultimate anti-Segawa weapon?
（本田）早く行ってこい！
（太郎）ラジャー！
Just get going!
They're bringing it by car.
It'll take around two and a half hours.
Roger!
Episode 9's cutting?
９話のカッティング…
No way. I have three meetings in a row with animators starting at 16:00.
俺 無理　16時から３件
作打ちが入ってるんで
Terribly sorry for the delay.
I could go after 19:00.
19時以降なら
But cutting starts at 17:00.
I'll let you know once it arrives. Thank you.
カッティング始まるのは17時…
Should I go?
（興津）
私が行きましょうか？
Aren't you in general affairs?
（本田）
興津さん 総務なのに？
残業しない主義なのに？
And don't you refuse to do overtime?
いいんですか？
Miyamori-san,
宮森さん 絵コンテとアフレコ台本
give me the storyboards, the recording scriptbook, and the time sheets.
タイムシートをください
Rest assured, Miyamori!
よかったね みゃーもり
もう９話は心配いらないよ
Episode 9 is in safe hands now!
Okay...
あっ はい
Okitsu-san, why not return to active duty?
興津さん やっぱ もっかい
現場に復帰したらどうっすか？
That's not happening. This is only a one-time deal.
（興津）
それはないです 今回だけです
Thank you very much!
よろしくお願いします！
Komoro Studio Ltd
So I made it on time? I'm glad to hear that.
（百瀬(ももせ)）
いや～
間に合ったみたいでよかったよ
Thank you very much!
（あおい）
本当にありがとうございました
Here, I made some quiche.
It's a thank-you for the Shinshuu noodles.
（丸川(まるかわ)）
これキッシュ焼いたの
信州(しんしゅう)そばのお返し
Share it with the others.
Momose Isamu
Komoro Studio President
みんなで食べて
やった　うちのが
好きなんだよね これ
Thanks! My folks love this.
Say hello to Sacchan for me.
Marukawa Masato
President
さっちゃんに よろしくね
Will do.
（百瀬）
うん 伝えとく
That reminds me, how's Sugi-chan?
そういや 杉ちゃんは？
Same as always. Still quiet and dignified.
相変わらずだよ　悠々自適
I see. Glad to hear.
そっか いいことだ
I'm looking forward to the airing!
放送 楽しみにしてるよ
お気をつけて
Take care!
Episode 4 Deadline Day
Exodus!
Episode 4    Cuss at Me More!
Musashino Animation
Watanabe Jun
Line Producer
Katsushiro
Goutarou
Maker Producer
Ah, Honda. Hey, it's Watanabe.
（渡辺(わたなべ)）
あっ 本田　渡辺です
They just finished with the preview.
うん はい お疲れ
今 プレビュー終わりました
I see. I'll be sure to tell her.
へえ～ 伝えておきますね
はい お疲れさまでした
Thank you. Bye.
Episode 4 made it. They sent it off to the station.
４話 完パケたって
納品に向かったそうです
Thank you!
お疲れさまでした
You can let the people you had on standby for retakes go now.
（本田）
４話リテークで
待ってもらってた人たち
バラしていいから
Okay, I'll do that now!
はい 早速！
Um...
（あおい）あの…
（本田）うん？
（あおい）
本田さん 今回は
本当にありがとうございました
Honda-san, thank you very much!
うん　あのね もっと
なんでも言ってくれていいから
You know, you can ask us anything. Don't just struggle alone.
一人で抱え込まないで
俺 心配性だけど一応
司令塔だから これでも
I might worry a bit too much,
but I'm still in charge here. Kind of.
Right. Sorry.
はい すみません
I messed up so much...
もう なんか失敗ばかりで
You've only just started.
（本田）
これからよ これから
I've never heard of production staff who've never messed up.
失敗しないで成長した制作なんて
俺 知らないもんね
Right.
（あおい）はい
（本田）そんで―
You'll soon be running projects smooth as butter!
I have great expectations for you!
早く うまく回せるようになってよ
期待してるから
期待…
Expectations...
Also,
（本田）あとね～
（あおい）うん？
I heard that the director cried during editing...
（本田）
監督 Ｖ編でさ　泣いてたって
あるぴんのカット
at Alpine's cut.
…だよな～
Thank you very much! Episode 4 is finished!
ありがとうございました
４話 完パケしました
I'm done!
Good job!
（山田）終わった～
（堂本）お疲れさま
It worked out after all.
（遠藤(えんどう)）
なんとか なるもんっすね
Endou, wanna go drinking?
Is that you, Ishirou? Can you call Mom, please?
（山田）遠藤 飲み行くか
（佐倉）大志郎か？
Sure, but is episode 9 gonna be all right?
（佐倉）ママさんに替わって
（遠藤）いいっすけど
９話は大丈夫なんすか？
（山田）
今日ぐらい いいだろ
One day won't hurt!
Exodus!
Episode 4
Final
Shirobako
Sunday? Sure, it's perfect for me!
（あおい）
うん！　日曜！
私は全然 大丈夫
Ema and Rii-chan should be okay too.
絵麻とりーちゃんも
オーケーなはず
Great! Then let's meet in Kichijouji!
（しずか）
やった～ じゃあ吉祥寺(きちじょうじ)に集合ね
I'll call Mii-chan.
みーちゃんには
私から連絡しとく
Thanks! I'm looking forward to it!
（あおい）
サンキュー　楽しみ！
うん じゃあね
Yeah! See you!
（あおい）流すよ
（絵麻）うん
Let's watch it!
Exodus!
Episode 4    Cuss at Me More!
Musashino Animation
Exodus!
Episode 4    Cuss at Me More!
Musashino Animation
I knew.
（あるぴん）私 知ってた
（お姉さん）あっ！
I knew that she worked for Ginger!
私… お姉さんが
ジンジャーの人だって知ってた
I knew!
私 知ってた！
This is Musashino Animation.
No soliciting, please.
Next time on Shirobako: "I Screwed Up Badly."
I Screwed Up Badly
（興津）
はい 武蔵野アニメーションで
ございます
セールスは間に合っております
次回「SHIROBAKO(シロバコ)」